hi i'm amanda perna at the amanda perna
and today i'm going to show you how to
hem your pants it's a good way to save a
lot of money and be able to have pants
that fit you perfectly
now depending on the type of pan and the
type of fabric you are going to want to
use different kinds of hems
for today i'm going to show you how to
do a top stitched machine hem which is
perfect for denim and other thick
fabrics or any time that you're okay
seeing the stitching marks you might
want to do a blind hem either by machine
or hand if you're doing something that's
a little bit more delicate or a little
bit more formal
the first thing you need to do is put
the pants on and measure them
you want to make sure you have them on
with any kind of shoe that you're going
to be wearing because if you're wearing
something taller you're going to want
them to be a little bit longer than if
you're wearing them with something flat
so i like to try them on a few different
things that i might possibly wear them
with and then find the happy medium so i
made two marks i like to mark my pants
when they're on me
on the two outside seams so that way if
one gets rubbed off you still know where
it is
the key to this is once you have the
spot you want is to go from the bottom
and measure up and try to keep it
consistent
so
i marked mine at approximately three
inches i like to round it up a little
bit just to be safe so now what i'm
gonna do is
i'm gonna mark it all the way across at
the three inch mark
i like to use taylor's chalk but you
could also use the pencil kind there's a
million different types that you can
play around with and see what you like
best um but this kind always works out
the best for me so now i have my line
this is going to be
where i want it to stop so in order to
make your hem this kind of hem is a half
inch
turned back twice so what we want to do
now is go from the finished mark
and go down half an inch
and this is going to be for our first
turn up
and then we're going to go down
another half so this is your seam
allowance so now we're going to go down
another half inch
[Music]
and make our mark
so this mark is going to be where we're
actually going to cut it
so that you
have your hem
[Music]
across here
you want sharp scissors
so that it's nice and straight
and that is going to be our cut part of
it
if you have an iron what you want to do
is press it all the way at half an inch
so you can also mark it as you go
with your ruler
you're going to want to trace your line
all the way around
and i like to use a pin here just so
it's really stable
so we're going to do it
and you can put as many pins as you need
to stabilize
so now we're going to do
the back side
we're going to make our little marks
now that i have both sides pinned here
what you're going to do is roll it again
and that's going to be your finished
place
so the good thing is because it's a half
and a half you you can actually use the
bottom as a guide
if it's easier for you you could turn
your pant inside out i don't think it's
necessary but i know some people like to
do it that way so what i do is i will
roll it
[Music]
sometimes it's easiest if you do it at
the side seam first
and we're going to pin so remember this
is our final stitching length so you'll
have that little guide of your
marking
and we're going to roll it and you want
to make sure you pull it tight and you
get it right to that line
this is when you see your jeans why
there's that little bit of bulk at the
bottom because of the fabric it makes it
a little bit thick and when you're doing
it make sure you're keeping it as
straight as possible
especially if you're using something
like the denim that i have that has a
little bit of stretch you want to make
sure it doesn't get pulled out of
rack because then the whole pant gets
skewed when you're trying to sew so you
only want to gently do it you don't want
to be pulling it too much in any
direction
you want to make sure your side seams
match up if it's easier for you could do
that at the beginning i like to go
around the circle but i've also been
doing this for a long time
you always want your pins on the outside
so that way when you're sewing you can
pull them as you go
[Music]
and if it makes it easier for you to
stabilize you can put pins closer
together and just remember the more pins
you put in the more you're going to have
to take out once you're sewing
so we have it all pinned neatly and this
is where you can once again iron it flat
if you have an iron at home i'm doing it
the simplest way possible so if you
don't have all the tools you can still
hem your pants but the more you iron the
smoother it is
so you're going to do the same thing on
the other leg
and then we're ready to sew
now we're all pinned and it's time to
start sewing i like to think about what
i want the final look to be do i want
the thread to blend into the pant
or do i want it to be more similar to
the original
i for this one i'm going to pick a color
that's kind of close to the original
stitching color now you can get super
perfect with it and take your pant and
match it or you could use a thread that
you have at home
so we're going to use a gold color
when you're doing this you want to make
sure that you also are paying attention
to your stitch length
they can be smaller or larger when
you're using something with stretch i
like to do something that's a little bit
longer in stitch length so that way when
it pulls because of the stretch it's not
held so tightly so i'm just going to
adjust this on my machine i'm going to
put it at a 3.5 but you could even go to
a 4
or if you want it really tight so it
doesn't move you can do it a smaller
length but remember you want it to
stretch it's the good thing about
stretchy jeans
and now when you're stitching you want
to pull your
pins out as you go so it doesn't break
especially since this is such thick
material you're already going to have a
little bit of a challenge trying to get
it in there
you want to stitch it a little less than
half so that way it catches all of your
fabric that is right at that half inch
mark
so you're going to put your needle down
i'm going to pull my pin first pin out
you want to pay attention and make sure
that you are not catching the leg
especially if you have a smaller
skinnier jean like i do here it's going
to be a little tight so you want to make
sure that you're constantly checking so
you don't stitch your leg shut
so we're going to go ahead i will
sometimes
also
go over really thick parts with
my hand wheel so that way it doesn't go
too quickly you want to make sure always
that you do a little back stitch so
we're going to go one
two
and
now
we're ready to go
pulling your pins
[Music]
okay we're getting to that side seam
again
so you want to get your hands
ready to get your hand wheel
unless your machine is powerful enough
to push through it which mine happens to
be if not if you're a little nervous use
your hand wheel and go slow
checking again as we go
[Music]
okay you're meeting at the same spot
that you started
back stitch
and cut
so
here we have our new hem
so beautiful and you can press this flat
again too
you're gonna hem the other side
and that's all there is to it you can
save all the money have a ton of fun
sewing and hem all of your pants right
at home i'm amanda perna thanks for
watching